<document>
	<date>2005-06-12</date>
        <title>Pellete de liens du 12-06-2005</title>
        <author>NiKo</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>signets</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>Liens</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
  
   
     un peu sombre | haifax 2004 
    Flasheur balaise. 
    (Tags:  flash   portfolio ) 
  
   
     Plugin Veni Vidi Vici - Tortue GT :: Extime 
    Un plugin qui s'inspire et remplace le plugin Lecturique 
    (Tags:  dotclear   plugins ) 
  
   
     Faites-vous une idee sur Windows et Linux 
    Pour se faire une veritable idee sur la question, il ne faut pas croire sur parole cet article, mais installer Linux et se faire sa propre opinion. 
    (Tags:  linux   windows ) 
  
   
     polices de caracteres gratuites et libres de droits a telecharger 
    Les 303 polices de caracteres presentes sur
   ce site sont freeware, autrement dit libres de droits,    vous pouvez donc les telecharger et les utiliser en    toute liberte et surtout en toute legalite ! 
    (Tags:  libre   fonts ) 
  
   
     Welcome to LinkedIn 
    With LinkedIn, you find the people, jobs and services you need through the people you know and trust, while you strengthen and extend your existing network. 
    (Tags:  community   network   online.tools ) 
  
   
     Traffic Control 2 
    Change the traffic lights to prevent traffic jams in this online flash game. 
    (Tags:  flash   jeu ) 
  
   
     Ultra Block - 2 Flash Games 
    Click on block groups of three or more to destroy them but avoiding clicking singles and doubles. 
    (Tags:  flash   jeu ) 
  
   
     ban comic sans :: Putting the Sans in Comic Sans 
    In 1995 Microsoft released the font Comic Sans originally designed for comic book style talk bubbles containing informational help text. Since that time the typeface has been used in countless contexts from restaurant signage to college exams to medical information. These widespread abuses of printed type threaten to erode the very foundations upon which centuries of typographic history are built. 
    (Tags:  fonts   microsoft   haha ) 
  
   
     #ProgX - CD Case 
    Cette image est generee par un script PHP a partir d'une couverture de CD telechargee chez Amazon. 
    (Tags:  php   dev   gd ) 
  
   
     REKTOR.NO / PRINCESS 
    THE WORLDS FIRST MUSIC VIDEO GAME! 
    (Tags:  flash   fun   jeu   haha ) 
  
   
     Google Fight : Make a fight with googleFight 
    "Combat" entre deux occurences de mot-cles dans Google. Peut eventuellement servir a valider une orthographe ^^ 
    (Tags:  google   fun   online.tools ) 
  
 

 
   
 
        </text>
</document>
