<document>
	<date>2005-06-13</date>
        <title>Pellete de liens du 13-06-2005</title>
        <author>NiKo</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>signets</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>Liens</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
  
   
     Windows vs Linux: a modern desktop comparison 
    We've put together a series of Windows XP, SUSE 9.3 and Ubuntu 5.04 desktop screen shots as a side-by-side comparison of some of the common desktop features available in the modern operating system desktop. 
    (Tags:  libre   windows   interfaces   ergonomie   ubuntu   desktop   xp   suse   utilisabilite ) 
  
   
     Icon Story 
    Animation flash rigolote. 
    (Tags:  flash   animation   fun   icones   haha ) 
  
   
     OS X for x86 already in the wild? - Engadget - www.engadget.com 
    Apple had OS X for Intel machines, and not a week after its announcement, a developer version? is apparently already in the wild on P2P and IRC networks. 
    (Tags:  apple   p2p   intel   osx ) 
  
   
     linux was my co-pilot - a photoset on Flickr 
    They had to cycle the power on the plane as I was getting on, lo-and-behold, Song (Delta) is using Linux to run the seatback entertainment. Did I mention Microsoft paid for my flight? 
    (Tags:  linux   fun   flickr   microsoft   haha ) 
  
   
     S5: A Simple Standards-Based Slide Show System 
    S5 is a slide show format based entirely on XHTML, CSS, and JavaScript. With one file, you can run a complete slide show and have a printer-friendly version as well. 
    (Tags:  css   conception   xhtml   presentation   webstandards   gestion-de-projet ) 
  
   
     Dangerrrr: cats could alter your personality - Health - Times Online 
    THEY may look like lovable pets but Britains estimated 9m domestic cats are being blamed by scientists for infecting up to half the population with a parasite that can alter peoples personalities. 
    (Tags:  medecine   chats   maladie ) 
  
   
     Services_Blogmarks PHP Toolkit - BlogMarks.net : Blog 
    We just released a PEAR Class which connect to the blogmarks.net API. 
    (Tags:  blogmarks.net   php   classe   php.lib ) 
  
   
     Airtight News  Blog Archive  De-gunk your Windows XP 
    Here is an easy way to speed up your Windows XP machine. When you install new software, many programs will set themselves (or helper programs) to auto-start every time you reboot. 
    (Tags:  windows   xp   tweak ) 
  
 

 
   
 
        </text>
</document>
