<document>
	<date>2005-06-15</date>
        <title>Pellete de liens du 15-06-2005</title>
        <author>NiKo</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>signets</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>Liens</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
  
   
     KnoWare, Inc. - Award Winning Internet Utilities and Software Since 1996! 
    Internet Neighborhood Pro, the world's most popular FTP client for Windows Explorer, gives you the ability to connect to FTP servers through the familiar WIndows Explorer interface. 
    (Tags:  windows   network   soft   ftp   storage ) 
  
   
     RoamDrive (beta) 
    Use GMail as an online storage unit. 
    (Tags:  gmail   windows   soft   storage ) 
  
   
     PEAR::Flickr_API 
    une classe php (Pear) pour interroger l'api flickr 
    (Tags:  photo   php   dev   flickr   classe   php.lib ) 
  
   
     99ROOMS.COM 
    Very nice point-and-click adventure in Flash. 
    (Tags:  flash   jeu ) 
  
   
     XFN - XHTML Friends Network 
    XFN (XHTML Friends Network) is a simple way to represent human relationships using hyperlinks. In recent years, blogs and blogrolls have become the fastest growing area of the Web. 
    (Tags:  xhtml   network   community ) 
  
   
     LXer: Ubuntu Linux Desktop Reviewed 
    "My first exposure to Ubuntu Linux occurred on forums, mailing lists and in the press. Friends told me that a great deal of hype existed around the distribution. I saw some criticism saying that Ubuntu was just another flavor of Debian. So, I basically dismissed it from the list of distributions I test. After all, we have seen new distributions of Linux crop up and die rather quickly." 
    (Tags:  libre   review   linux   ubuntu ) 
  
   
     Bulletin hebdomadaire allergo-pollinique de Paris 
    AIRPARIF - Pollens - Surveillance des pollens dans l'air 
    (Tags:  paris   health   allergie ) 
  
   
     Equivalent javascript des proprietes de CSS - Tellaw.org 
    Voici une liste assez complete des equivalents entre les appels javascript et les proprietes de CSS. 
    (Tags:  javascript   css ) 
  
   
     resources.neolao.com/flash/classes 
    Classes AS2 de NeoLao. 
    (Tags:  flash   dev   actionscript   flash.lib ) 
  
   
     resources.neolao.com/php/classes 
    Classes PHP de NeoLao. 
    (Tags:  php   dev   classe   php.lib ) 
  
   
     Upload files to your mobile phone - Free file upload service on wap - mobstorage.com 
    1. Upload your file
2. Get the item code
3. Go to wap.mobstorage.com and download 
    (Tags:  storage   mobility   online.tools ) 
  
   
     CoolMon - system stats on your desktop 
    CoolMon is a program for monitoring vital system stats and almost anything else you wish to display on the desktop. 
    (Tags:  windows   soft   monitoring ) 
  
   
     foobar2000 
    Foobar2000 is an advanced audio player for the Windows platform. Some of the basic features include ReplayGain support, low memory footprint and native support for several popular audio formats. 
    (Tags:  musique   windows   son   soft   player ) 
  
   
     Article : Jabber, une autre facon de voir l'IM 
    Nee de l'Internet Relay Chat (IRC), la messagerie instantanee ne cesse de se developper avec les annees et voit les naissances de MSN, Yahoo! Messenger, AIM et... Jabber. 
    (Tags:  jabber   messenger ) 
  
   
     Upload and crop your photos, web graphics, Skype / MSN / Yahoo avatars. No more Photoshop! 
    Upload and crop your photos, web graphics, Skype / MSN / Yahoo avatars and much more. Forget Photoshop! 
    (Tags:  photo   online.tools ) 
  
   
     01net. - Les escrocs se mettent a la prise de fichiers en otage 
     Certains de vos fichiers sont codes. Pour acheter le decodeur, envoyez un mail a [...] . C'est le message que PGPCoder laisse sur les PC de ses victimes afin de tenter de leur extorquer de l'argent. 
    (Tags:  hack   malware ) 
  
 

 
   
 
        </text>
</document>
