<document>
	<date>2005-06-08</date>
        <title>Pellete de liens du 08-06-2005</title>
        <author>NiKo</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>signets</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>Liens</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
  
   
     Favicons 
    Une collection de Favicons (icones d'URL)
     (categories:  icones ) 

   
     Apple to Use Intel Microprocessors Beginning in 2006 
    Apple to Use Intel Microprocessors Beginning in 2006
     (categories:  apple ) 
  
   
     O coin du feu : Photos, liens multimedias, forum 
    Site fourre tout sympa
     (categories:  blog   photo   forum ) 
  
   
     As2lib * Welcome * Open Source ActionScript 2.0 Library 
    As the leading ActionScript 2.0 application framework, the As2lib delivers significant benefits for many projects, reducing development effort and costs while improving test coverage and quality
     (categories:  flash   dev   actionscript   flash.lib ) 
  
   
     Complex Dynamic Lists: Your Order Please: A List Apart 
    In our struggle to reduce the number of steps site visitors must take to accomplish their goals, we face a number of challenges. One of them is to provide a good way for users to choose from a list of hierarchical elements.
     (categories:  javascript   css   accessibilite   conception   css.menu ) 
  
   
     Main Page - WikiPodLinux 
    This page provides the details of an open source venture into porting Linux onto the iPod
     (categories:  libre   linux   son   ipod   baladeur ) 
  
   
     3DFS - 3D Flash Studio - A 3D Engine in AS2 
    3DFS is a 3D engine written in AS2 (ActionScript 2) compatible with Flash Player 7.0 or more.
     (categories:  flash   dev   3d   flash.lib ) 
  
   
     CSS Formatter and Optimiser/Optimizer (based on CSS Parser CSSPP 0.95) 
    CSS Formatter and Optimiser
     (categories:  css   webdesign   online-tools ) 
  
   
     QuirksMode - CSS 
    CSS contents and browser compatibility
     (categories:  css ) 
  
   
     Generating an SSL Certificate with Apache+mod_ssl 
    This document is intended to be a quick guide to generating and installing an SSL certificate on an Apache web server with the mod_ssl module
     (categories:  web   apache   ssl ) 
  
   
     deviantART: garGANTuan by *epicbard 
    so what is it? Its a GANT theme for Gnome.
     (categories:  gnome   theme   icones ) 
  
   
     eHow.com 
    Clear Instructions on How To Do (just about) Everything
     (categories:  howto   tutorial   faq   moteur ) 
  
   
     Kinja, the weblog guide 
    Kinja is a weblog portal, collecting news and commentary from some of the best sites on the web. Visitors can browse items on topics, everything from food to sex.
     (categories:  rss   blog   agregateur   online-tools ) 

   
     Darwinia 
    Jeu compatible linux
     (categories:  linux   3d   windows   jeu ) 
  
   
     Javascripts 
    Javascript Snippets
     (categories:  javascript   dev   snippets ) 
  
   
     
    We're Big John and Holly Bergevin, and together we built this site to explain some obtuse CSS bugs in modern browsers, provide demo examples of interesting CSS behaviors, and show how to 'make it work' without using tables for layout purposes
     (categories:  css   webdesign   layout ) 
  
   
     Firebird - Relational Database for the New Millenium 
    Firebird is a relational database offering many ANSI SQL-99 features that runs on Linux, Windows, and a variety of Unix platforms.
     (categories:  linux   sql   windows   bdd   firebird ) 
  
   
     JavaScript 2.0 Classes 
    Classes are defined using the class keyword. Limited classes can also be defined via JavaScript 1.5-style functions, but doing so is discouraged for new code.
     (categories:  javascript   dev ) 
  
   
     How To Disable GreaseMonkey On Your Web Site 
    Insert that little script in your page and GreaseMonkey is no more.
     (categories:  javascript   firefox   greasemonkey ) 

 
 
   
 
        </text>
</document>
