<document>
	<date>2014-02-13</date>
        <title>[Revue de tweets] MGS Ground Zeroes fonctionne mieux sur PS4 que sur Xbox One</title>
        <author>Kocobe</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>Hideo Kojima</tag>
                <tag>Konami</tag>
                <tag>Metal Gear Solid V : Ground Zeroes</tag>
                <tag>PS4</tag>
                <tag>Xbox One</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>G&#233;n&#233;ral</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
                                                                                                 
         
                 Sur Twitter, les petits chanceux qui ont pu finir  MGS Ground Zeroes  donnent leurs premi&#232;res impressions. 
 more 
 Et la premi&#232;re, qui semble avoir &#233;t&#233; confirm&#233;e par Kojima lui-m&#234;me, est que  Metal Gear Solid V: Ground Zeroes   tourne mieux sur PS4 que sur Xbox One  dans l&#8217;&#233;tat actuel des choses. 
 @SMayorga9293  I'm only playing on PS4, but I think Mr Kojima has already said that the PS4 version is smoother than the One version. 
 &#8212; Douglas (@DouglasNerd)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 Get Ground Zeroes on PS4, not XB1. Way better visuals, frame rate, everything&#8230; I believe  @HIDEO_KOJIMA_EN  said so himself.  #MGSVGZNasu 
 &#8212; Dazz Loyall Brown (@TheVGResource)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 Il semblerait aussi que si le jeu ne &#171;&#160;dure&#160;&#187; que 2&#160;h, les qu&#234;tes annexes sont l&#233;gion et peuvent &#234;tre tr&#232;s cons&#233;quentes. 
 Finished GZ for the first time in about 90 minutes. Total game completion? 9%. I think that tells you all you need to know.  #MGSVGZNasu 
 &#8212; Sam Smith (@Crunch_King)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 @ItsCelebrity_   @Konami  The game doesn't play like a standard MGS game in this sense. Several missions, each range from 30 mins to 2 hours. 
 &#8212; Dazz Loyall Brown (@TheVGResource)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 Tout le monde s&#8217;accorde &#224; dire que  MGS Ground Zeroes  ne poss&#232;de pas la structure narrative classique de la saga et que c&#8217;est une bonne chose. 
 The whole thing feels faster paced as a result, less reliant on cutscenes with more storytelling through gameplay. It's great.  #MGSVGZNASU 
 &#8212; Sam Smith (@Crunch_King)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 D&#8217;autres ont bien aim&#233; la fin aussi. 
 Metal Gear Solid V: Ground Zeroes.

Just saw the ending. Goosebumps. Disbelief. Shock. *reboots game* I'm going back in.  #MGSVGZNasu 
 &#8212; Samuel Hubner Casado (@Spainkiller)  13 F&#233;vrier 2014 
 
 
 Il semblerait donc que  MGS Ground Zeroes  soit parti pour &#234;tre un excellent jeu. C&#8217;est en tout cas le jeu  new gen  que j&#8217;attends le plus &#224; titre personnel 
         
 Source 
                                                                                                         
                                                                                                                                                                                                 
        </text>
</document>
