<document>
	<date>2012-04-27</date>
        <title>Un nouvel hymne pour les geeks : I'm the one that's cool.</title>
        <author>Aelya</author>
        <tags_set>
                <tag>i'm the one that's cool</tag>
                <tag>chanson</tag>
                <tag>paroles</tag>
                <tag>the guild</tag>
        </tags_set>
        <categories_set>
                <category>Geek</category>
                <category>S&#233;ries</category>
        </categories_set>
        <text>
 
 
 &#160; 
 Je suis une grande fan de The Guild (je regarde depuis les d&#233;buts). 
 J'avais ador&#233; leurs pr&#233;c&#233;dentes chansons :  
 Do you wanna Date my Avatar  est une vraie merveille et me sert de sonnerie de t&#233;l&#233;phone pour Quantic (apr&#232;s tout, nous nous sommes rencontr&#233;s sur un MMO). 
 Game On!!  est elle-aussi excellente, surtout avec son c&#244;t&#233; Bollywood. 
 J'&#233;tais donc toute contente lorsque j'ai d&#233;couvert (avec un peu de retard) qu'une nouvelle chanson &#233;tait sortie ce mois-ci ! 
 I'm the one that's cool!  est en quelque sorte la revanche des geeks sur ceux jug&#233;s populaires. C'est tr&#232;s am&#233;ricain, mais reste vachement sympa^^ 
 
 Bonus n&#176;1 : les paroles^^ 
 1ST VERSE: Oh, no. Don&#8217;t pretend I didn&#8217;t see You roll your eyes at my gaming tee Don&#8217;t know if you can read or if you&#8217;ve seen The sweet piece in this week&#8217;s Wired magazine The latest trend has hit its peak They say that geek&#8217;s becomin&#8217; chic So now you&#8217;re out of style as you can be And I&#8217;m in vogue, so you can bite me To all the ass-hat jocks who beat me up in school Now I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool To all the prom queen bitches thinking they still rule Now I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool 2ND VERSE: Try to cop my style but I&#8217;m the real thing While you played sports, I played Magic the Gathering See you pose a part of nerd society My Aquaman pajamas prove my pedigree Star Trek: Next Gen every night Wore a headgear to fix my overbite Your black-rimmed glasses are prescription free, where as me I literally can&#8217;t see my hand in front of my face To all the asshat jocks who beat me up in school Now I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool To all the prom queen bitches thinking they still rule Now I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool And to my eighth-grade crush who pushed me in the pool Now I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool You may be tan and fit and rich but you&#8217;re a tool And I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool I&#8217;m the one that&#8217;s cool 3RD VERSE: Role reversal must be a total drag But there&#8217;s no point, no point for me to humblebrag I appreciate you for being cruel I&#8217;m burning bright thanks to your rejection fuel Got my in-jokes you won&#8217;t get Like Honey Badger, Troll Face and Nyan Cat So now your ballin&#8217; parties seem so dumb You can Evite me, and I&#8217;ll say yes, but I won&#8217;t really come Got my comics Got my games All the things you thought were lame Got my cosplay Fanfic too Got you pegged STFU You CHORUS 
 En second bonus, je ne peux pas r&#233;sister &#224; l'envie de vous mettre les deux chansons pr&#233;c&#233;dentes^^ 
 
 
 
 
 
 
        </text>
</document>
